{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "George Stoneman’s failure at this battle may have been the reason for the Union defeat. Oliver Otis Howard’s 11th Corps were encircled in this battle when Stonewall Jackson secretly moved around their flank. The Union commander at this battle quipped, “May the Lord have mercy on General Lee for I will have none,” shortly before his troops were forced back across the Rappahannock River. For ten points, Joseph Hooker was defeated by Robert E. Lee in what 1863 battle near a Virginia village?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Chancellorsville",
        "Chancellorsville campaign A"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this country, students wore yellow T-shirts to protest increased phosphorite mining in L¨a¨ane-Viru [LAH-neh VEE-roo] County. This country experienced the Era of Silence under Konstantin Pats in opposition to the Vaps Movement. This country’s army, led by Johan Laidoner, fought together with the White Russians in a War for Independence that was ended by the Treaty of Tartu. For ten points, name this nation where people demonstrated at the Tallinn Song Festival Grounds.",
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Estonia",
        "Eesti Vabariik"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A prime minister from this party supported a 10% goods and services tax in his country and served R four terms from 1996 to 2007. Robert Menzies and Malcolm Fraser were among the leaders of this party, as was Tony Abbott during the tenure of Julia Gillard when this party was the Opposition. In a 2019 election, this party’s leader, Scott Morrison, was elected as prime minister. For ten points, what is this Australian political party that opposes Labor?",
      "answer": "Liberal Party of Australia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This policy was expanded by the Scott Act, which prohibited re-entry to the United States. Support for this act was drummed up by Denis Kearney and the Workingman’s Party. This act was preceded by D the less-comprehensive Page Act and later repealed by the Magnuson Act. Supporters of this act blamed “coolies” for depressed wages in places like San Francisco. Chester Arthur signed this act into law in 1882. For ten points, name this act that barred immigration from a large Asian country.",
      "answer": "Chinese Exclusion Act"
    },
    {
      "question": "The “best antidote” to this religious movement was drowning, according to Holy Roman Emperor Ferdinand I, who ordered the execution of Michael Sattler, the writer of this movement’s Schleitheim Confession. The Hutterites, Mennonites, and Amish are all offshoots of this religious movement. For ten points, name this Christian movement from the Radical Reformation and associated with Thomas Muntzer, that opposed performing a certain water based sacrament on infants.",
      "answer": [
        "Anabaptism",
        "Anabaptists,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader was opposed by “Jafari the Brainless” and the Rashidian brothers. This leader resigned after his Minister of War nomination was blocked, prompting the leftist Tudeh Party to take to the streets. Kermit Roosevelt helped disseminate firman declarations opposing this leader. MI6 and the CIA joined forces to overthrow this leader in Operation Ajax after he nationalized the AIOC. For ten points, name F this secular Prime Minister of Iran who was overthrown in a 1953 coup.",
      "answer": "Mohammad Mossadegh"
    },
    {
      "question": "This song plays over the opening credits of Stanley Kubrick’s film Paths of Glory. The lyrics to this song implore, “Let’s march, let’s march,” and it opens with the words “Arise, children of the fatherland.” Phrases from this song and “God Save the Tsar” are repeatedly used to represent opposing armies in Tchaikovsky’s 1812 Overture. Patrons of Rick’s American Cafe sing this song to drown out the Nazi A soldiers in the film Casablanca. For ten points, name this national anthem of France.",
      "answer": "La Marseillaise"
    },
    {
      "question": "A bust of this man in “Severe style” is considered the “first true portrait of an individual European.” In one plot, this man fled Greece after being implicated as a co-conspirator with the treasonous Pausanias. This general at Marathon was elected archon and called for increased emphasis on his city’s naval power, which proved instrumental at a 470 BC battle against the forces of Xerxes the Great. For ten points, name this leader of Greek forces against the Persians at the Battle of Salamis. R",
      "answer": "Themistocles"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the aftermath of this event, Robert Hunter wrote, “One way or another, this darkness got to give” for the track “New Speedway Boogie.” During this event, Paul Kanter sarcastically thanked security for smashing “Marty Balin in the face.” A video crew recorded a stabbing during this event, footage of which was used in the documentary Gimme Shelter. The Hells Angels provided security for the Rolling Stones at, for ten points, what failed “Woodstock of the West,” a 1969 free concert in California?",
      "answer": [
        "Altamont Free Concert",
        "Altamont Speedway Free Festival,",
        "Altamont Affair D"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Hap Arnold was among the founders of this company, which was created partly out of fear that SCADTA could provide control of the area around the Panama Canal Zone to Germans. In a 1977 tragedy on Tenerife, a Dutch owned vehicle operated by KLM collided with one owned by this company. Beginning in 1960, this airline operated out of the Worldport terminal at JFK. For ten points, name this airline which, prior to its collapse in 1991, was the largest airline in the United States.",
      "answer": "Pan American World Airways T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this battle, an attack from the south forced one commander to flee across Brouwer’s millpond. American troops were forced to use their muskets as cFlubs against oncoming Hessian troops at Battle Pass during this engagement. Israel Putnam was promoted prior to this battle, which occurred four months after the Siege of Boston. Though William Howe won this battle, George Washington was able to flee across the East River from Brooklyn Heights. For ten points, name this 1776 battle.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Long Island",
          "Battle of Brooklyn Heights before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "General Howe used this island as a staging point for the Battle of Long Island. Sparsely inhabited at the time, this 102 square mile island is today home to nearly half a million people. A",
        "answer": "Staten Island"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This organization engaged in a form of urban guerrilla street fighting called kale borroka. Several members of this organization were condemned to death in the Burgos Trials. This group carried out Operation Ogre, which resulted in the bombing and assassination of Franco’s chosen successor, Luis Carrero Blanco. Two Ecuadorians were killed by this group in the 2006 Madrid-Barajas Airport bombing. Officially dissolved in 2018, for ten points, name this Basque separatist group.",
        "answer": [
          "ETA",
          "Euskadi Ta Askatasuna,",
          "Basque Homeland and Liberty R"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the best known Basques in history is this sainted author of the Spiritual Exercises who co-founded the Jesuit order with another Basque, Francis Xavier.",
        "answer": [
          "St. Ignatius of Loyola",
          "either underlined portion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Baiju’s victory over this empire at the Battle of K¨ose Dag resulted in this polity’s takeover by the Mongols. Iznik was the first capital of this polity whose founder, Suleiman ibn Qutulmish, was killed by the brother of Malik Shah. Suleiman’s son, Kilij Arslan I, led this empire when they defeated Peter the D Hermit’s untrained peasants at Civetot in the People’s Crusade. Named after its Eastern Roman subjects, for ten points, name this sultanate that broke off from the Seljuk Empire in 1077.",
        "answer": "Sultanate of Rum"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Historians debate whether credit for starting the Crusades should be give to Peter the Hermit or to this French pope who promised pardon for sins to those who fought the Muslims.",
        "answer": "Urban II T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this region, Daoud Bolad led a separatist movement after disputes over hakurat land rights in the 1980s. Slovene activist Tomo Kriznar was arrested for videotaping atrocities committed in this region. The Zaghawa and Masalit ethnic groups have been forced to flee this region. The Janjaweed militias have been accused of violence in this region while under the command of Omar al-Bashir. For ten points, name F this region, the location of the genocide of thousands of non-Arabs in Sudan.",
        "answer": [
          "Darfur",
          "War in Darfur",
          "Darfur genocide"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1994, Omar al-Bashir worked with the French to capture this notorious Venezuelan terrorist who admitted to the deaths of 80 people, which he said was “for a cause, the liberation of Palestine.”",
        "answer": [
          "Carlos the Jackal",
          "Ilich Ramirez S´anchez A"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After being forced to flee Nazi Germany, this philosopher stated that only “the gloomiest predictions have any plausibility.” This philosopher claimed that the “damaged life” had led to fascism in his book Minima Moralia. This student of Alban Berg had plans to complete Berg’s opera Lulu and notably dismissed jazz as part of the “culture industry.” For ten points, name this German Marxist philosopher, who collaborated with Max Horkheimer on Dialectic of Enlightenment.",
        "answer": "Theodor W. Adorno"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Adorno was a member of a “school” of philosophers located at Goethe University and named for thisRGerman city, Goethe’s birthplace and home to the Institute for Social Research.",
        "answer": "Frankfurt am Main"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this battle, a group of nearly 2,000 mercenaries under Philibert of Chand´ee proved instrumental to the winning army. The Stanley family assisted the victor in surrounding the losing army of this battle. Henry Percy was briefly imprisoned after this battle, where he served under a man who killed the Princes in the Tower. The future Henry VII was the victor at this battle which resulted in the death of Richard III. For ten points, name this 1485 battle, the last major engagement of the Wars of the Roses. D",
        "answer": "Battle of Bosworth Field"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Shakespeare’s Richard III, Richard is known by this ducal title he held in real life that refers to an English cathedral city on the River Severn.",
        "answer": "Duke of Gloucester T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One process named for this man includes lipolysis and creates butyric acid to stop fermentation. In 1937, dairy farmers attacked striking workers at a factory owned by this man. This man started a namesake “Industrial School” for orphans in Pennsylvania. This man sold D-Bars to the army during World War Two, as well as a more flavorful “Tropical” bar that would not melt at temperatures over 90 F degrees. For ten points, name this founder of the Lancaster Caramel Company.",
        "answer": "Milton Snavely Hershey"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man, who ran a competitor of Milton Hershey’s, developed M&M’s after seeing soldiers during the Spanish Civil War eating a similar British candy called “Smarties.”",
        "answer": "Forrest Mars, Sr. A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "High taxes and corruption accusations led to this man being replaced by Nathaniel Higginson as President of Madras. At the request of Increase Mather, this merchant for the British East India Company sent a painting of King George I and over 400 books to a fledgling institution founded in 1701. That institution containing the Skull and Bones society was named after this man in 1718. For ten points, who is this man who names an Ivy League institution in New Haven, Connecticut?",
        "answer": "Elihu Yale"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Three U.S. presidents have received their undergraduate degrees from Yale, the Bushes and this 20tRh century president whose father was U.S. Attorney General and Secretary of War.",
        "answer": "William Howard Taft"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Benedict Arnold",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Military post on the Hudson River that he attempted to give to the British F",
          "answer": "West Point"
        },
        {
          "question": "1777 battle at which he helped defeat John Burgoyne’s invasion of New York",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Saratoga",
            "Battle of Bemis Heights"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Article of clothing honored at that battlefield, marking where Arnold was wounded in the leg",
          "answer": "Boot Monument A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fort on Lake Champlain that he helped the Green Mountain Boys capture in 1775",
          "answer": "Fort Ticonderoga"
        },
        {
          "question": "British officer who was hanged for assisting Arnold",
          "answer": "John Andr´e"
        },
        {
          "question": "Philadelphia socialite who introduced him to that officer and later married Arnold",
          "answer": "Margaret “Peggy” Shippen R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish general who died while providing Arnold reinforcements at the Battle of Quebec",
          "answer": "Richard Montgomery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Besieged New York fort which Arnold tricked Barry St. Leger into abandoning",
          "answer": [
            "Fort Stanwix",
            "Fort Schuyler D T"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ypres [EE-pruh] in World War One",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country in which Ypres is located, on France’s northeastern border F",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Belgium"
        },
        {
          "question": "Weapon whose first widespread use by Germany was the Second Battle of Ypres",
          "answer": [
            "Chlorine gas",
            "poisonous gas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Allied 1918 offensive which shares its name with Napoleon’s post-exile campaign",
          "answer": "Hundred Days A"
        },
        {
          "question": "British commander at the Third Battle called the “Butcher” for his costly offensives",
          "answer": "Douglas Haig"
        },
        {
          "question": "German offensive whose 1918 Operation Georgette aimed to capture Ypres",
          "answer": [
            "Spring Offensive",
            "Kaiserschlacht,",
            "Kaiser’s Battle,",
            "Ludendorff Offensive"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Village that gives an alternate name for the Third Battle R",
          "answer": "Passchendaele"
        },
        {
          "question": "Skirmish during the Second Battle that shares part of its name with the British War Secretary",
          "answer": "Battle of Kitcheners’ Wood"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term used to refer to the destruction of German student reservists in the First Battle",
          "answer": [
            "Massacre of the Innocents",
            "Kindermord D T"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Asian Piracy",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Final Chinese dynasty, during which Asian piracy reached a peak F",
          "answer": "Qing dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island also known as Formosa where the pirate Koxinga took Fort Zeelandia",
          "answer": "Taiwan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pirate-ridden Malaysian shipping channel once ruled by a namesake sultanate",
          "answer": "Straits of Malacca A"
        },
        {
          "question": "First kingdom to unify Korea, which used Jang Bogo’s pirate fleet for protection",
          "answer": "Silla"
        },
        {
          "question": "Female pirate who led 80,000 pirates in the China Seas",
          "answer": [
            "Ching Shih",
            "Cheng I Sao"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Indian empire where admirals like Kanhoji Angre harassed the East India Company",
          "answer": "Maratha Empire or Confederacy R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tamil dynasty ruled by Rajaraja that allowed pardoned pirates to enlist in their navy",
          "answer": "Chola dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of pirates on the Korean coast that was crushed by the Oei Invasion",
          "answer": "Wokou D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this man had a dispute with his sister-in-law, Dagmar Havlov´a, he sold his fifty percent stake in the Lucerna Palace on WencFeslas Square that his grandfather built. This leader started several dissident initiatives including the (20 pts)",
        "Charter 77 and the Committee for the Defense of the Unjustly Prosecuted. This man led the Civic Forum when it dominated the first free election in (10 pts)",
        "Czechoslovakia in forty-four years in 1990. For ten points, name this man, the namesake of the international airport in Prague and the first president of the Czech Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "Vaclav Havel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A senator from this state was the lead singer of the barbershop quartet The Singing A Senators. That senator was arrested in the Minneapolis airport for soliciting an undercover police officer in 2007, which he defended by claiming that he had a (20 pts)",
        "“wide stance.” Another senator from this state prosecuted Big Bill Haywood in the trial following the murder of this state’s governor, Frank Steunenberg. It’s not Massachusetts, but that man from this state led the (10 pts)",
        "Irreconcilables in opposition to the Treaty of Versailles. For ten points, name this home state of Larry Craig and William Borah."
      ],
      "answer": "Idaho 3RJulius Caesar Chappelle gave a speech at this building in 1890 promoting a federal law to allow Blacks to vote. The namesake of this building inherited a massive shipping empire, because he went against his uncle’s wishes and chose + not to marry. This building is named after a slave trader from a Huguenot family. The site of many patriotic speeches, a noted Ann Whitney statue of one of those speakers, * Samuel Adams, stands at its eastern end near a statue of Mayor Kevin White. For ten points, name this “Cradle of Liberty,” a meeting hall in Boston. ANSWER: Faneuil Hall D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The murder of a member of this family was investigated by Floribert Chebaya after which he was also killed. A man from this family was supported by posters that read in French, “Here is the man we needed.” (20 pts)",
        "Che Guevara said that man from this family lacked “revolutionary seriousness.” Moise Katumbi, former Katanga governor, tried to run against a member of this family, but his house was surrounded by police. In 1997, (10 pts)",
        "Mobutu Sese Seko was replaced in office by a member of this family named Laurent-D´esir´e. For ten points, name this Congolese family that includes D.R.C. president, Joseph."
      ],
      "answer": "Kabila family T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Early in this man’s career, he failed at making saddles and repairing clocks. This artist spent three years studying painting with Benjamin West before returning to Maryland and joining the (20 pts)",
        "Sons of Liberty. This man organized the first U.S. science expedition and founded the Philadelphia Museum. This polymath had sons named Titian and Rembrandt F and painted a self-portrait titled The Artist in His Museum. This man is perhaps best known for depicting (10 pts)",
        "men like Nathanael Greene and Thomas Jefferson in his portraits of Revolutionary War figures. For ten points, name this patriot and painter."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Willson Peale"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man popularized the term “Middle East” after publishing an article on “The Persian Gulf and its International Relations.” One work by this officer, inspired by Antoine-Henri A Jomini, advocated for the usage of (20 pts)",
        "“decisive battle” and blockade. Some have argued that use of this man’s theories led to the Japanese defeat in World War Two. This man’s writing inspired Alfred (10 pts)",
        "von Tirpitz to plan for the annihilation of the Royal Navy, sparking an arms race between Germany and Great Britain. For ten points, name this American naval officer who penned The Influence of Sea Power Upon History."
      ],
      "answer": "Alfred Thayer Mahan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this period, The Mayor of Zalamea was written, as was a play centered on BaRsilio, the heir to the Polish throne. During this period, two poets who promoted rival styles of “culteranismo” and “conceptismo” also flourished. Those two poets of this period were Luis de (20 pts)",
        "G´ongora and Francisco de Quevedo. Other works from this period include a pioneering picaresque about Lazarillo de Tormes and (10 pts)",
        "Life is a Dream. For ten points, name this period in which Iberian playwrights such as Lope de Vega flourished during a period of wealth and power for their country."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spanish Golden Age",
        "Siglo de Oro,",
        "Golden Century D"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was victorious against Chnodomar at the battle of Argentoratum, allowing him to re-establish the Rhenish frontier. This man wrote the Misopogon essay, recalling an incident in which the residents of Antioch mocked him for his beard. This (20 pts)",
        "emperor died when he was struck by a spear during his invasion of Sassanid Persia, leading to the ascension of Jovian. This man wrote the essay (10 pts)",
        "Against the Galileans, a stern rebuke against Christianity. For ten points, name this Roman emperor who received a sobriquet for his attempts at a pagan revival."
      ],
      "answer": "Julian the Apostate T"
    }
  ]
}